Benson Okiora

Android Developer

LinkedIn: linkedin.com/in/bensonokiora/

Tel: +254718621991

Email: bensonokiora@gmail.com

SUMMARY

As a Senior Software Engineer at Wahi Africa, I help many users manage their daily bills and earn rewards with an offline-first financing platform. I work on new features, testing, deployment, and A/B testing, using the latest Android architecture and RESTful APIs.

I have six years of experience in building native Android applications and back-end systems for fintech and e-commerce companies, such as Shopy Africa, where I designed and developed a robust Kubernetes solution for online store creation and management. I am a self-starter, an enthusiastic team player, and a problem-solver, with a keen interest in learning and teaching. I have a Bachelor's degree in Software Engineering from kisii university and multiple certifications and honors from Google and other organizations.

EXPERIENCE

Wahi Africa, - Senior Software Engineer

April 2021 - May 2023

In this role, I help build a financing platform from scratch that offers many users a way to manage their daily bills easily. The app's main focus was to fully work offline and help users earn back from every transaction they made, from paying bills to sending money to any bank within East Africa. I was responsible for the following:

- Developing new features, conducting testing, and deploying updates to ensure a seamless experience for millions of users
- Implementing A/B tests to measure and evaluate the impact of various improvements
- Working to improve our C|/CD processes and increase test coverage
- Developing an innovative solution to enable users to utilize the app offline to manage their transactions fully
- Integrating RESTful APIs with 30+ fintech bank systems

The financing platform was designed to offer millions of users an easy way to manage their daily bills and earn rewards from every transaction they made, including paying bills and transferring funds to any bank within East Africa. The app's primary focus was to operate fully offline.

Shopy Africa, - Software Engineer

March 2020 - April 2021

In this role, I improve the lives of people who own businesses to easily manage their online presence. Shopy offers a way to create, promote, and manage an online store using a mobile app. I helped build the Android app and a Kubernetes backend.

- Designing and developing the Android app using the latest Android architecture
- Designing a robust pattern for the adoption of Kubernetes technology for the ROA orchestration solution, which was highly scalable, secure, fault-tolerant, cost-optimized, highly available, and self-healing, leveraging DigitalOcean
- Led cloud projects in the design of event-driven solutions architecture, defining deployment strategy, implementing application metrics, and cost-optimized solutions using DigitalOcean Kubernetes Services
- Designing and implementing highly resilient, fault-tolerant, and scalable architectures for software solutions to be deployed in the cloud
- Drafting finOps for cloud workloads
- Setting up CI/CD pipelines using DigitalOcean native tools and undertaking test automations

In this role, I helped build the Android app and a Kubernetes backend for Shopy, a platform that allows business owners to easily create, promote, and manage an online store using a mobile app.

Kedevelopers Tech Ltd, - Software Engineer

Jan 2018 - March 2020

Using my vast experience in Mobile Development to drive the building of solutions using emerging technologies with deep expertise in modern application development for a wide range of Industries. In this role, I was responsible for the following:

- Providing solutions to clients in a variety of industries, including android app development, web development, cloud provisioning, platform architecture, and administration
- Overseeing mobile development processes and contributing to quality assurance and code reviews
- Proposing and implementing technical solutions to improve performance and scalability

I have a proven ability to work effectively in teams and have a strong focus on delivering high-quality solutions to meet the needs of our clients.

Nilinde Ltd, - Software Developer (Part-Time)

Feb 2018 - Aug 2018

As a Software Developer at Nilinde, I utilized my expertise in mobile app development and database design to contribute to the development of a platform that helps the public report crimes using their mobile devices in real-time. My efforts helped improve the efficiency and effectiveness of the Nilinde platform and contribute to the safety of communities.

- I Designed and published mobile apps, including the Nilinde user app and police app, to facilitate the reporting of crimes using mobile devices in real-time.
- Worked on the web portal to offer real-time feedback on crimes and improve the efficiency of reporting and responding to crime-related incidents.
- Contributed to the development of tests and CI/CD pipelines to ensure faster deployments and maintain the reliability of the Nilinde platform.
- Designed and developed the database architecture and Nilinde API to support the functionality of the platform and enable seamless integration with other systems.
- Utilized innovative technology to improve the efficiency and effectiveness of the Nilinde platform and help keep communities safe.

Sphinx Pharmaceuticals Ltd, - Android Developer

Jan 2017 - Dec 2017

As an Android Developer at Sphinx Pharmaceuticals, I played a key role in the development of an innovative mobile app that significantly impacted the company's revenue. My responsibilities included:

- Implementing user interface, location service, and core data, as well as integrating RESTful APIs.
- Navigation features, and Google Maps functionality to create an Uber-like experience for users.

Through my contributions, the app effectively located employees' selling points and helped the company save a significant amount annually.

Kenya Power Ltd, - Android Developer

May 2016 - Sept 2016

As an intern, I helped the company continue working on the products to achieve its milestones and deliverables for a series of apps

- Worked on an Android app to manage employees' medical allowances.
- Worked with NFC Cards and Fingerprint authentication integration to the core app
- Improved features in Kenya Power's core systems

SKILLS

Android Development, Kubernetes, Springboot, Node.js, Amazon Web Services (AWS), Google Cloud Platform (GCP), Firebase, Java, Kotlin, Git, C#, Docker, SQL, Database Management

EDUCATION

Kisii University- Bachelor's degree in Software Engineering

2013 - 2017

• Focused on software engineering and mobile development.

Certifications

- Letter of Commendation Google
- Android Developer Course Skillvalue

Volunteering

DSC Lead, - Developer Student Clubs

May 2016 - Sep 2017

- Organize and teach mobile development to fellow students.
- Participated in Hackathons, Local Hacks, and Workshops, facilitating training and imparting Web and Mobile Development skills.
- Google Tech Speaker.
- Created an active developer community to solve community problems.

Professional Speaker, - Atlassian Community Events Nairobi

Feb 2018

- Organize and teach Atlassian tools to the community.
- Created an active developer community to solve community problems using Atlassian tools.

Android Mentor - Kisii University

Feb 2016 – Apr 2018

• Created an active developer community to build apps.

Playstore / Appstore Apps

• Wahi:

https://wahi.africa/ https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.wahi _mpesa

- Shopy App: https://shopy.africa
- Kedevelopers:

https://play.google.com/store/apps/dev?id=6489968701471 797534